So, you tap a button and something happens
— that’s how the world works, right?
Well, not exactly.
The world is actually filled with buttons
that are only there to seem like they do something,
while in fact being useless.
And not only buttons — there are all kinds
of things that are there for no apparent reason.
1.
Pedestrian crossing buttons
If you live in a big city, you’ve probably
seen these buttons placed right beneath a
huge sign saying “Press the button and wait
for green light” or something like that.
I don’t know about you, but I always diligently
press it, although it doesn’t always work
as it should.
Or does it work at all?
The thing is, transport authorities sometimes
switch off the functionality of these traffic
buttons on purpose.
In New York, for example, there are 1,000
of them, but currently only 100 actually work
when you press them.
All the rest are no more than a decoration.
They’re often called placebo buttons because
all they do is create an illusion of control:
you press a button and you expect that something
will happen, while not knowing that the process
is automatic.
Such buttons have an important psychological
effect: doing something feels better than
not doing anything.
When you press the button at a crossing, you
feel more assured that the light will eventually
switch to green.
Otherwise, who knows?
Maybe it will keep being red forever?
In any case, some of these buttons do work,
and no one will tell you exactly which ones
don’t, so not to feel stupid just standing
there and waiting, better press the button
anyway.
Why they turned them off in the first place,
though?
Because the traffic lights system turned out
to be much more complex, especially in big
cities.
If you drive, you could notice that sometimes
you get in a “green wave,” when every
traffic light lets you go ahead.
It happens when you adhere to the speed limit
and there are no obstacles on your way (like
busy unregulated crossings).
But if there’s a traffic light with a working
crossing button, it can turn red at any moment,
and your “green wave” will be over.
So, not to disrupt the work of the whole network,
many of the traffic control switches were
turned into placebo buttons.
2.
Elevator door close buttons
If you live on, say, 15th floor and you’re
in a hurry to get home because your bladder
is about to burst, for example, you’ll probably
feel fine running up the stairs.
But if you decide to wait for the elevator
instead, you’ll smash that door close button
until the doors finally close.
Which they will do awfully slowly.
Sorry to disappoint: not all close buttons
are equally effective.
In the US, these buttons don’t work at all.
The elevator doors will stay open for no less
than the time appointed to them, no matter
how much or how long you mash that button.
The roots of this lie in the legislation,
in fact: the 1990 Americans with Disabilities
Act stated that elevator doors should remain
open long enough for anyone with any movement
impairment, be it a wheelchair or crutches,
to get inside without trouble.
So unless you’re an emergency service worker
or just happen to know the override code,
you won’t be able to make the doors close
faster.
Maybe it’s best to take those stairs, after
all.
If you live outside the US, though, your chances
of getting a working close button are much
higher.
In many countries, there are no such strict
regulations, so you can easily find an elevator
where, if you press the door close button,
the doors will actually shut immediately.
As an added bonus, if you press the door open
button right after that, they’ll stop midway
and open again!
Oh wonders of technology.
3.
Thermostat control in hotels and offices
Most white collars will agree with me: having
a thermostat in the office is a necessity,
not a luxury.
And sometimes there are veritable battles
going on between those who like to keep it
cool and those who would rather sweat than
shiver.
Which one is you, by the way?
Share down in the comments!
But the truth is much more… sly, I think
is the word.
You see, most office buildings have a central
heating, ventilation, and air conditioning
system (HVAC for short).
And the thing about this central system is
that you can’t actually affect it from anywhere
outside the control center.
In fact, there are two general types of office
thermostats: one that is total placebo and
one that is only partially so.
The total placebo type speaks for itself:
whatever it shows on that little digital screen
is a lie.
You can press the buttons all you like, and
the numbers will change, but the temperature
will remain the same.
The partial placebo thermostat has a little
bit of sway: it can change a couple degrees
in both directions, but no more than that.
So if you press the button to decrease the
temperature from 72°F and it goes all the
way down to 60°F, rest assured that in reality
it stops at somewhere about 70°F. You will
hear the vents whirr, though, and the machinery
will seemingly come to motion.
That and a slight drop in temperature create
the feeling that you’re really in control.
The placebo effect is in that you believe
something’s changed, and your body reacts
accordingly.
Same goes for many hotels too: if your room
is equipped with a thermostat, you can be
sure it only creates a semblance of activity,
while keeping the room temperature the same
whatever you do.
4.
Progress bars
Whenever you download a file from the Internet
or install a new app on your device, you see
a bar that informs you of how much time you
have left to wait.
Ever seen it stuck at 99% for, like, forever,
though?
Yeah, it’s exactly what it seems: the progress
bar is always wildly inaccurate.
One of its creators, Brad A. Myers, said that
the purpose of the bar was never to show the
actual progress.
Its main aim was — and still is — to soothe
the users.
And they don’t seem to mind at all!
According to the tests Myers conducted with
his team, users didn’t care that the progress
bar was inaccurate — they just preferred
having anything to show the progress was really
made.
When nothing happened on the screen, they
got the feeling that something went wrong
or their download wasn’t working at all.
Honestly, I’d start mashing keys myself
if I saw just a blank screen too.
5.
Calorie counters on treadmills
What a pleasant feeling it is to run on a
treadmill and watch calories melt away in
real time!
Only this melting might not be exactly what
you expect.
When you run, you burn calories for sure,
but the precise amount depends on various
factors, such as your weight, overall fitness,
and body fat percentage.
What you see on the screen is another placebo,
I’m afraid.
In this case it’s not entirely useless,
though: the calorie count shows you the average
of what you could get if you were of, well,
the average build.
This counter is, once again, only there to
assure you that you’re doing everything
right.
The downside of this is that even if you’re
not doing it right, the treadmill won’t
let you know.
That’s why depending solely on the machinery
is not recommended — hire a personal coach
for best results.
6.
Graceful failures
Now this isn’t so much about the illusion
of your control as it is about you being calm.
Does it make you mad when you see an error
message on the screen of your PC or other
device?
Me, it sure does!
Well, many companies have found a way out
of this inconvenience.
For example, if you turn on some app that
has personalized recommendations and they
fail for some reason, you won’t even know
about it.
Instead, you’ll see a screen with popular
choices, which are likely to appeal to you
as well.
And it all started in the 1960s, when the
1ESS phone system was invented in the US.
When a call attempt failed, the system didn’t
tell the caller about it, but simply switched
to another recipient instead.
So when somebody took the phone on the other
end of the line, you apologized for dialing
a wrong number and tried again.
This way, you didn’t feel the frustration
of having a failed call.
So…now you know.
Hey, if you learned something new today, then
give the video a like and share it with a
friend!
And here are some other videos I think you'll
enjoy.
Just click to the left or right, and stay
on the Bright Side of life!